hello and welcome
everybody it is October 18th
2023 and we're here in active inference
guest stream 59.1 with David Tucket on
conviction narrative Theory so David
thank you for joining very much looking
forward to this presentation and
discussion so to
you so thank you very much just perhaps
a bit of useful background is that uh uh
I'm someone who started out as an
economist in the days when economists
were taught more than they are now that
is to say also sociology even a bit of
politics and then I became a medical
sociologist while at the same time
becoming a psychoanalyst which may I
won't attempt to explain but it's
obviously different and then um in more
recent years I've tried to put those
things together with going back to
economics and trying to understand
particularly financial markets but more
generally uh decision making and how it
works are sort of on the big scale so
conviction narrative theory is the
outcome of this kind of exercise uh I
suppose it's it most immediately started
from the fact that uh I began uh a
series of interviews but perhaps I'll
just come to about that in a minute so
what is conviction narrative Theory the
purpose of it is that it tries to
characterize the social and
informational context in which decision
making occurs and secondly the cognitive
and affective processes governing it so
it's about how people actually take
decisions not how they ought
to this book here minding the markets
was a book I uh published in
2011 and was the outcome of 52
interviews with fund managers those are
people who work for some of the large
firms like Goldman Sachs or others and
were responsible for investing at least
500,000 uh dollars into the world stock
market some of them invested as much as
20 20 billion so they ranged and when I
was talking to them I became aware that
the they were very intelligent people
they often had up to 20 people
supporting them who are also very
intelligent and able they had lots and
lots of computer power and programs and
analytic schemes and so forth but when
it came down to it what they had to do
was to make a judgment and they had to
be convinced about that judgment and not
only that they had to hold to that
judgment over time which is something
that's not often discussed in decision
making so if you if you decide to sell
or buy or even hold any kind of
investment that's a decision you make
at0 one but usually it's not going to
pay off for you or the whole idea is it
won't pay off for three five 10 years
and so you've got to be willing to stick
with your decision for quite a long
period of time or if you decide you've
got it wrong
to back out and all of this requires
what I I realized requires what I call
conviction so that's the basis of where
this Theory started
from so real world decision making which
is what we're trying to understand here
uh is best understood by example for
example the one I've just given how to
manage an Investment Portfolio but also
a question like what level of reserves
does a bank need to be safe a decision
ision like should you expand your
company into a new product or new
technology or how much funding should a
university or a company allocate to
cyber security threats what resilience
standards should be adopted by
government
regulation precisely what should we
prepared to do to prevent catastrophic
climate change how should we anticipate
and prevent future potential financial
crisis or how do you level up uh regions
of your country or the world which are
currently unequal these are all pretty
big big questions and I would argue all
of them involve
uncertainty so they're massively
consequential choices that's the first
point the data is always going to be
incomplete the options are ambiguous and
the
future that is what you know has
happened so far not only may not
resemble the past but in our modern
world World which is changing rapidly is
actually unlikely to resemble the past
or you could put it another way which
bits of the past will it resemble and
which which it
won't for all these reasons the axioms
of standard decision Theory are not
satisfied in this
situation now the choices that require
to make choic in this situation require
both commitment and monitoring so as to
adapt smartly over time as events unfold
so in the investment example I began
with you have to be willing not just to
make the decision but to stay with it
it's a bit like a marriage or any other
kind of long-term choice of course you
can get out of it but the point of doing
it is to is to try and stay with it and
then it'll also involve monitoring that
is trying to assess if in fact you've
made the wrong decision so you adapt
pretty quickly over time as in events
unfold
now the context for such choices can be
labeled as radical uncertain radically
uncertain because data may or may not be
useful and could even mislead now we
should be able to say just uncertain or
even we should be able to say risky but
the problem is these words uncertain
uncertainty risky have all become given
very specific meanings uh in different
disciplines which makes it extremely
confusing but the underlying Point here
is that I'm talking about a situation
where the future is yet to be made and
so it must be imagined however you're
going to do
that okay now conviction narrative
Theory which tries to address this
situation is designed as an alternative
cross-disciplinary theory of decision
making that starts from the proposition
that human cognitive affective and
social capacity ities are well adapted
for uncertain
context a great deal of the existing
research at least in Psychology has
tended to uh demonstrate that humans are
not very good at decision- making do all
kinds of experiments which show that
they have biases they frame things
incorrectly they don't use statistics
properly uh they get emotional Etc but
by the time you finish reading all that
research you wonder well how do we get
where we are you might be you might be a
bit say yeah well look where we are but
if you look at the advances that that
has been made by humankind clearly we're
rather good at at making new decisions
and at developing new things and there
must be something wrong with a theory
which fundamentally talks about bias and
one of the ways of thinking about that
is to think that perhaps we're adapted
to the real world better than we are
adapted to the kind of world we set up
in Labs or the kind of gambling
decisions that typically uh decision-
making Theory tries to start with so in
both labs and gambling decisions there
is a right answer or at least there's an
answer that consensually people would
tend to say was the best the best choice
to make so what conviction narrative
Theory does and I'll come to it in a
moment is it turns the core issue from
how to make best decisions which is
typically what search has been looking
up to now to how to make any decisions
at all given the need to act when in
fact there's a possibility of facing
loss or failure real loss or real
failure real disasters so how do people
do it when they can't so to speak be
certain or feel there's a really good
chance of things working and the answer
is that they adopt a conviction
narrative and I'll try to to explain
that but the basic idea is they adopt of
course a course of action which they
believe to be sorted uh supported by a
narrative which convinces them that by
adopting that course of action they will
get to the outcome they want now on the
whole people don't invent conviction
narratives just out of thin air what
they actually do is they adapt
narratives that is ideas about what
actually are effective for the
particular thing they're trying to do
from those already circulating in their
networks could be in their company in
their social group
Etc now one of the key things that
conviction narrative is theory is
designed to direct you towards is that
if you accept that the basic way people
make decisions is by trying to adopt a
conviction narrative because of the need
to act then what becomes interesting is
how do they do this and in order to
begin thinking about that the theory
postulates two particular states of
people or of organizations that you come
back to in which this conviction is
generated one is called divided and the
other integrated I'll try and explain
them more detail but integrated
basically means where people bring all
the information available uh to bear and
they're as sensible as they can about it
they realize what they're doing they
know it's uncertain but they're still
able to make major commitments so it's
kind of the academic Nana if I should
make decision making divided is where
for one reason or another people only
consider part of the story part of the
outcomes
Etc and what conviction narrative theory
is designed to do is to kind of alter
the way way we approach these problems
and so identify different kinds of ways
uh for doing
research okay now a central a central
idea that follows from all this is the
idea of ambivalence and this is an idea
that I do get from from psychoanalysis
so it's also used otherwise and
ambivalence is an intrinsic property of
any human relationship if you consider a
marriage an employment contract or just
about anything which lasts for any
length of time you will tend to have at
any given time feelings to in favor of
doing it and feelings against doing it
it's pretty normal that is feelings
generate approach or avoidance but of
course there'll be an overall level at
any one time of one or the other once
you get avoidance you get out of it once
you have approach and you basically go
on doing it and this is based on work
going back to Freud or the sociologist
Neil
smelson now decision making in radical
uncertainty necessarily evokes causes
people potentially to be ambivalent
because while time is unfolding once
you've made the
decision the outcome of your actions
continues to be uncertain an exanti you
quite simply cannot know the answer and
that inevitably creates anxiety and
anxiety creates avoidance so there's
always a tendency to want to stop what
you're doing perhaps or if it's the
other way around and you decided not to
do something the argument that maybe you
should have can can come back so
consequently contemplating action to
exploit a perceived opportunity must
stimulate a greater feeling of approach
than avoidance pretty simplistic Theory
but in other words approach feelings
generate lots of let's do it kind of
feelings and avoid avoidance feelings
trigger loss aversion inhibition and
withdrawal or a defense against that I
just being
blind conviction narrative Theory CNT
Focus attention really on how this
ambivalent situation which I want to
stress is both affective and cognitive
is dealt with
and as I mentioned before the divided
State or the integrated state are two
ways of thinking about it you could
think that if you accept radical
uncertainty then most decisions really
are
experiments and if you play with that
idea it's quite interesting because
making decisions in so to speak
experimental mode is rather different
than making decisions in in other modes
because if you're doing it in
experimental modes it mean that from the
start you would perhaps build into the
situation as you do with an experiment
ways of measuring what's going on giving
you feedback formalizing your hypothesis
as to why you think things are going to
work out and then uh uh getting some
sort of feedback as to what's actually
happening now obviously one trick here
the trick that's but which most
disastrous potentially is you simply
eviscerate doubt so that uh and one of
the problems is that a lot of modeling
decision a lot of modeling that is
called for in public decision making is
often used whatever the modelers might
have intended to actually get rid of D
oh my model tells me it's all right to
do it sort of
thing okay so to say a little bit more
I've used the term narrative and and so
it's worth trying to say what is
actually meant by that in our Theory
narratives are structured higher order
mental
representations which
incorporate all of causal temporal
analogical and veilance information
about agents and events which serve to
explain data imagine and evaluate
possible Futures and motivate action so
it's their quite a lot of things that
look like
narratives which aren't narratives
unless they have the potential to do all
those things that I've I've just read
out it it may not always be in the
narrative but it is there potentially
for it to be a narrative so you know you
would tell a story about what would be
the effect of giving this talk for
example now narrative fragments are
subsets of the elements in a narrative
which can be readily communicated so it
doesn't seem to us after a lot of
thinking about it and study that there's
very much to be gained from uh trying to
decide what when is it a big narrative
when it's a small narrative when it's a
narrative when it's a story to have to
recognize that narratives tend to be
made up of other narratives of smaller
fragments on which the main n narrative
depends the second important concept is
shared narratives
uh what I'm getting at here is that uh
there are narratives that are shared
within social networks which are so to
speak do dominant so in a particular
group this is the way we do things this
is the way we understand things science
is lots of shared narratives which
govern scientific methodology for
example third important term is
explanatory models this is taken from
social anthropology and explanat models
are culturally valid valid systems of
understanding often ex expressed as
narratives so for example a theory of
economic growth is explaining how
economic growth takes place a theory of
coid infection and so
on finally The crucial a crucial concept
is feelings and this is based on the
idea that feelings and modern
neurosciences demonstrated this pretty
strongly that feelings are at the center
of all brain activity that is most
things you can observe when you look at
brain you know brain scans and things
like that you typically see Mo movements
between different parts of the brain and
often going through uh parts of the
lower brain uh Etc the amydala and areas
of that kind the function of feelings it
seems is that they force their way way
to Consciousness in the human brain and
they prioritize conflict resolution in
context and this is particularly
important it's especially important for
economists who for example have a a
theory of utility because I think what
we learn from uh what we know about
feelings in the brain is that your
utility function Alters according to
context and the brain is is sort of set
up to do this so we actually have a
number of conflicting a
which where one or other is turned on
according to the particular context for
example uh to look after people caring
as opposed to enjoy ourselves and so on
and so
forth the overall effect is we feel we
want to approach or avoid uh including
when you're listening to me some of what
I'm saying may be sort of switching you
off completely where you may be
struggling to listen or even not want to
listen at all other bits may be making
you feel yes yes and this is going along
with whatever cognitive judgments you're
making as well so to summarize I don't
see although it's useful to to talk
about cognition and feelings maybe
separately they always operate
together uh that's a picture of the
brain to show the point I made which I
won't develop now but the the
fundamental point is that for a long
time in the 19 Century the brain was
understood the wrong way around that is
to say just because the cortex is on the
top there and information comes through
the core actually it's the the lower
parts of the brain which are fundamental
to conscious decision making and the the
uh the the cortical function is kind of
added on
top now there are four functions of
conviction narrative theor which explain
why conviction narratives work as they
do this slide doesn't seem to work so
the first function of a of a of a
narrative in conviction narrative is
explanation that the narrative imposes
structure on the current situation that
yields a sense of understanding and
emotional satisfaction so for instance
typically when people do science they do
all the stuff they do with the
methodology and so forth and they
present results but in doing so they
tell a story
about it explaining the situation and
that we do most stories have an
explanatory uh
quality the second element uh in a
conviction narrative is it allows a
mental simulation so for example if you
are thinking about shall I um shall I
adopt this particular way of trying to
do climate
mitigation I can think of the actions I
can imagine I can get all sorts of
spreadsheets and and you know proper
hard information and I can try and look
at what I think will be the outcome of
that particular activity in 20 years
time and as I do it in some way or other
I'll be forming at least implicitly
pictures in my mind of what the earth
looks like when I finish doing all this
and then you can compare an alternative
or many alternative narratives and so to
speak you run the narrative forward to
generate imagined Futures as associated
with a particular
choice the third which follows from what
I said about feelings is that these
explanations and mental s simulations
are evaluated effectively so you react
emotionally to the Futures you imagine
to evaluate their desirability and that
helps to manage commitment over time and
the fourth and really important function
of narrative in a conviction narrative
is communication most important big
decisions of the kind I'm interested in
involve a number of people working
together it could be several labs for
instance or it could be people working
to a particular aim in regard to climate
or or many other problems and so when
you work together with other people you
have to motivate them and you have to
explain to them and you have to give
them an idea of where you're going and
what the point is and we use narratives
for that and narratives that propagate
across social networks and U become in
that way maybe shared
narratives so the other thing I'd like
to stress is the conviction narrative is
not any old narrative it's a narrative
that sets out how you're going to change
the current situation by an action to
lead to a desired outcome okay it's very
spe and to do that you draw on
narratives in your in your your in your
context
so the narrative solve uh two particular
uh or or there are two sets of problems
in decision making if you think about it
we call this the logic of decision so
that decisions reflect both data picked
up from the external world including the
social environment and internally
derived goals so to make a decision
you've got to do both things you've got
to U pick up data and then add it to
your to your goals the first aspect to
this you can call the mediation problem
which in the diagram is the dashed
lines it reflects the need for an
internal representation what in our
paper we call a currency of thought that
can mediate between data from the
external world and actions decided
internally and one of the things about
economics for those who are economists
is e economics actually has as far as I
can tell no theory of cognition models
in economic you just write down um you
know R for real rates it doesn't have a
theory of how people come to know what
the real rates are and of course as soon
as you do have to fix such a theory
you've got lots of room for disagreement
and
differences second is the combination
problem which is the the lines and that
reflects the need for a process a driver
of action something to get you actually
doing something that combines beliefs
and goals to yield
actions and In classical Theory
classical decision Theory the currency
of thought is probability and the driver
of action is expected utility
maximization so you know if you've got a
probability of 70% of success and and
that that's good enough then what you're
supposed to do is to choose the highest
thing and that is a very seductive and
uh sensible way to make decisions
provided you think you've got
probabilities in behavioral economics
the main emphasis is on how people get
the wrong probabilities they make
decisions based on biases and so on that
they don't take the probabilities
properly into account in radical un
certainty that the argument is there
aren't probabilities or at least there
aren't probabilities for the kinds of
questions that I've been trying to talk
about so in CNT the currency of thought
we propose is narratives and the driver
of action is effective evaluation of
narratives in a social
context and this a rather complicated
slide to say something about about that
you see that you know we have data we
have the narratives we have this
explanation and simulation there's
affective evaluation leading either to
approach or avoidance link with your
goals and then you take action so that
representation and processes in
conviction narrative Theory narratives
supplied in part by the social
environment there a very important part
of the theory that we're picking up
narratives from around us all the time
are used to explain data they can then
be run forward in time to simulate
imagined future outcomes of action which
are then evaluated effectively
considering the decision makers goals
and these appraisals of narratives then
govern our choice to approach or to
avoid these imagined Futures and there's
a you see from the figure there's lots
of feedback
loops okay and I'll just talk a little
bit about divided and integrated States
so
uh as I mentioned this diagram is
supposed to uh
illustrate uh narrative prediction that
is what your narrative is going to tell
you to do as you get new
information based on where you started
your prior so in so far as the new
information you get is creates congruent
feelings to where you were before you
can pay attention to that data in an
integrated State you pay attention
whether it's congruent or not congruent
with your existing narrative in a group
Feld or divided State how it works is
you only pay attention to the things
that you already uh agree with in other
words confirmation bias and in congruent
Fe information that produces in
congruent feelings is ignored so this
this is how you get bubbles in finance
and Bubbles in lots of areas of activity
in society because if you don't if you
don't attend to the negative information
then that's the only way you can go now
bear in mind this can also work the
other way if for example you're in a
depressed or in a in a state where we're
not doing anything you can continue to
there you discount the positive
information and so you stay in a
repetitive bubble so an integrated State
group of Affair State of Affairs it is
is that envisaged in normative theories
of science based on experimentation and
or inference strategic actors are
curious a broad range of information and
perspectives both supporting and
challenging plans and actions are
considered and it's recognize that there
are uncertainties and contradictions
within the preferred conviction
narrative supportting a strategy or
policy and crucial to the integrated
state is the idea you know that although
you're making a decision it could be
wrong so you're open to new information
The Divided State I won't go through it
again is is just the opposite of
that okay and this is just a a last
slide to just give a quick uh link to
work that's been done particularly in
Psychology where you can see that this
whole theory is very dependent on what's
going on in your local social
environment because in your loal local
social environment there are various
narrative elements influencing your
evaluation of narratives so you know the
the stories that are around the his the
shared history of the group various
characteristics or Logics or frames or
conventions beliefs and so on which are
all uh but these interact with the three
things which have been found very uh
significant in in lots of psychology
what are called content effects that is
ways in which different content tends to
be picked up positively or not
trustworthiness effects that there are
all sorts of effects about listening you
know you can dress somebody up to look
like a professor and people are supposed
to believe them more as opposed to a
or something uh and presentational
effects which has to do with the way
things are presented and so on this can
influence whether a narrative is
convincing or not and overall you get
the the usual thing that It All Leads to
a narrative which either generates
approach or avoidance and only if
there's a positive balance do you go for
Action okay so that's roughly the theory
I hope it makes some sense and uh uh
generates some uh questions
all right
awesome okay well while I am cropping
and returning everything to normaly
visually how did you come to this I mean
what brought you through the the warps
and the weaves to want to highlight this
perspective well so first of all I think
when I was I was enough to study e
economics at King's College Cambridge it
been the College of John Mano KES and
when I was there it was still very much
we were taught by kan's pupils and they
saw economics as very much to do with
the management of uncertainty economics
today has defined uncertainty in such a
way that it doesn't have to take it into
account and so everything can have a
probability and so on so I I've always
felt
uncomfortable with what's happened in
economics because the real world seems
to me uncertain as I said earlier um you
know there's the whole point about human
Innovation and and the way in which new
companies are formed in an economy or
new scientific theories come about Etc
is is there new they may be
recombinations of the past but they are
they're new and and it it's not helpful
to have a kind of equilibrium theory for
for those sorts of problem however
useful it might be for other things and
so that was a general background um it
was through psychoanalysis that I came
to see the importance of feelings uh
most people when they think about
psychoanalysis probably haven't don't
know much about it or had a rather
half-baked explanation given but
actually what Freud's major contribution
is uh was that he
understood that so to speak feelings and
thoughts are intricately linked that if
the thoughts you're having make you feel
bad you'll do all kinds of things not to
have them or even not to need to have
have them in the first place so this
link between thoughts and feelings has
always been around it actually came in
part from his Neuroscience but in more
recent times it's now uh become I think
largely accept
uh view I gave this Theory the outlines
of this Theory to I tried out on Carl
friston who probably most of you know
about 10 or 11 years and Carl is a great
listener he sat there and he listened
for about 15 minutes and he looked very
thoughtful and then he said well there's
nothing you've said which is in
opposition to current Neuroscience so
that was nice that encouraged me to go
on anyway so uh also as as I've
mentioned when I began trying to
understand uh how could uh the do crisis
in in financial markets have come about
which I was studying just as the global
financial crisis was actually not
happening but about to happen it was
then that I realized and I think quite a
lot of people have realized it
afterwards that this kind of thing in
which people make decision based on
convictions they do the best they can
with the information they've got but by
its nature that what they do is
uncertain and therefore
fragile awesome yeah definitely wh while
there wasn't
any active inference generative models
in the talk you brought up so many
motifs that I think we can explore a
little bit because they're the kinds of
things that that as you pointed
towards necessitate a cognitive account
so first how how would you see cognitive
modeling playing a role in
microeconomics or macroeconomics like
what kind of cognitive model what kind
of explanation prediction or
intervenability do you
seek well so I I think I mean there's
there's no doubt that that um you know
as we as we go about our business we
form cognitive models of the world
around us and um that in my opinion
that's a useful way way way to think uh
and i' I've really called them
explanatory models because I first
encountered them in anthropology this
was when I did a big study in in the
late in the mid 80s
of um a thousand patients going to their
doctors and looking at what they'd
understood and to cut a long story short
although at the time it was widely
thought that patients didn't understand
most of what their doctors said and
therefore it wasn't really worth their
doctors spending much time talking to
them uh in fact what we found was that
most patients did understand what the
doctors uh were saying but that where
they didn't it was because the model of
understanding what was wrong with them
that the patient had so they had their
own model was not the same as the model
the doctor had and they hadn't
established the the two explanatory
models and then you know put them
together and in fact very often it would
have been quite easy for the doctor if
he knew what the patient was thinking to
point out that this that or the other
assumption or process as as we would say
you know wasn't how things worked and
then that would have helped the patient
to understand as it was the patient just
went away not quite understanding what
had gone on and often didn't follow the
treatment so that's how I got into if
you like cognitive models now when you
try to formalize
them uh uh you know I think it's extreme
it's extremely interesting to to try and
formalize them but I always have the
reservation that um you know where it's
always where we're getting the
information from and how robust is it to
changing circumstances so I mean that
that's the that's I think the key
problem cool so I was very
um interested by that provocative
example of the person making financial
decisions with with a 20 person
team that's a lot of attention and
energy a lot of skin in the game just
for that kind of an organization to to
deploy that kind of a decision support
setting so how do we think about that
what what works or doesn't when there's
group decision making and then how does
that integrated divided dialectic within
an IND indidual relate to the status of
the integrated or
divided understanding that might arise
at a group level especially if it's a
decision where like it's obvious from
the get-go that no no one of those
people know whether the stock is going
to go up or down so then what does that
20th person or the 21st person or the
22nd person do on that team to actually
empirically lead to better
outcomes that's a really it's a really
good question uh so and in order to to
to think around it there there certain
background facts that are important one
is that these people doing that work are
on the whole the most highly paid people
in our society which is which adds a
level of Fascination to your question
because we know we know from academic
research that no one
uh no there's no published data anyway
to suggest that anyone can consistently
do better than the average okay and the
reasons are obvious uh nonetheless
there's always hope right and so one of
the ways you could start to think about
it is is this uh supposing it's it's
your P supposing it's your pension and
you've got a choice to put the money in
something which will just get you the
average which of course will mean that
at times it'll go down and times will go
up ex you'll just get the
average versus somebody who says well
you
know I can do better than the average
look at my last year's results and they
last year's results will show better
than the average because obviously by by
statistics some people do better than
the average
so then it's quite difficult for people
it seems to say no to the possibility of
doing
better and that might be one part of the
story here but at the level of the the
people with 20
teams um
they they essentially are are paid to do
this work we know that they do it better
than you or I could do do it on average
so there there are studies that show
that individual investors don't do as
well as uh professional investors but
they are increasingly studies that
active investors that is people doing
sort of what I you know who look over
the data and try and decide what to do
that active investors in in fund
management don't uh on average beat some
form of more uh
computer-based automated way of doing it
which just looks at averages and so on
of course all of these methods fall
apart under certain situations uh
computer-based methods did terribly
badly uh at certain times and they have
done recently um so and we also know
that if you so that if you know what
private Equity if you heard of private
Equity or Venture Capital this is
another level which ordinary people
aren't allowed to invest in because it's
supposed to be
risky but where actually they often do
do better though uh because they've got
less money to play with and they can use
expert knowledge in particular areas
again it's subject to all the problems
I've talked about so why what what is
all this about and why are there all
these people engaged in and I think the
answer is that
there's a constant attempt to support
the
narrative that you know what do you do
with your money so I mean the
University's got University Pension
funds got to invest right your pension
it's got to be done somehow and uh uh
yeah I could go on a great deal because
I think the conclusion from this is that
it doesn't work very well and that's
because what people do is they pursue
what I call in the book fantastic
objects that is they become convinced
that you know the new way of doing
hydrogen technology or the new way of
doing this that or the other which is a
way which is promising but which nobody
knows enough about to be sure about
that's going to be the thing to make you
your millions and that's what you'll
invest in or there's ABC person who's a
fantastic investor he becomes a
fantastic object okay
so that what a fantastic object works
with group think in a divided state to
get rid of doubt and then create this
process I described earlier which is a
sort of self-fulfilling prophecy process
which works until it
doesn't cool another piece I found
really interesting is the laboratory
decisionmaking setting whether it's
reductionist or however you want to
characterize it it focuses on certain
kinds of decisions first off ones that
align well with the axioms of standard
decision Theory but just pragmatically
they tend to be these oneshot gambling
decisions or Game Theory decisions that
are really amenable to the kinds of
Matrix calculations and the nash game
theory and all of this yeah and yet
that is not how it feels to be making
decisions dayto day and then you brought
in the approach aoid so when the
gambling is in front of us and we only
have the decision-making Alternatives it
kind of removes this meta on the
decision like whether one even
approaches that slot machine or not
which is a much more nebulous decision
because everybody starts in a different
position and then also this
consistency which is really where
conviction comes into play with an with
the marriage or with the investing which
is even a decision at one time point is
really more like an agentic event in a
broader tapestry or narrative whereas in
the gambling setting it can lead one to
make models that are sort of
like decision next next next next and
it's like blank slay every single time
that a new decision is made and then
that has limited ability to transfer in
to all kinds of other situations that
you describe as having that radical
uncertainty like to the root rather than
a superficial uncertainty like whether
in this one narrow decision something
should happen One Way Or Not yeah
exactly I I think that's that's exactly
right and of course the
I mean it's not really to be negative
about all the stuff that's been done
because it's shown very interesting
things but I think the the main the main
issue is have you identified your
context correctly because we kind of
know I mean in the to go to sort of
basian stuff we as I understand it
although I don't fully understand how
it's really done uh there there's an
argument that that we're good Samplers
that we sample well locally people do on
the whole but of course the problem
comes when you get out of your
context and so the the I think the key
issue is sort of the
transferability of information or
Knowledge from one context to the other
some friends of mine Lenny Smith and um
Erica Thompson have written a paper
called
uh escape from modeland which is all
about how you know they're modelers he
he they do forecasting weather
forecasting and climate models and all
that but the question is there's lot you
know how do you get out of the model
into the real world and what challenges
do you then uh face I mean and that's
much more of course economic models are
much weaker than those kind of models
they're talking about so but it's a
context thing and how can you how can
you assess whether you've got the right
things in your model you've got the
right data Etc and these these are the
things where you tend to I mean the
financial crisis was partly caused by
people having the wrong
models but they'd seem right at the
time yeah well the AC of sampling a good
sampler is exactly what active inference
is about are is secades are in the
business of doing good sampling good
epistemic value and when the context
shifts like if you have a book and you
flip it upside down your icting is not
going to be making as good sampling and
that's why it's hard to read let me
exactly ask some questions from the chat
all
right Bert
asks there are many similarities with
scenario planning in transport policy
how could policy planning move from cost
benefit analysis
to the use of
narratives well that's that's a very
that's a very good question there's a
there's a
paper on the second paper down that
deals with Futures and foresight and
conviction ality Theory
but so the the problem with cost cost
benefit analysis is kind of a logically
sensible idea in which you know you try
to work out the costs of um of of a
project
and you try to work out the benefits and
then you work out whether it's worth
doing the problem is with all the
assumptions as obviously the questioner
realizes and in a formal cost benefit
analysis you have to make up lots and
lots of numbers in order to make it
formally work so I think the question is
whether you're using the cost benefit
analysis to have a
discussion about making a decision and
to open up ways of thinking and question
assumptions and all that kind of thing
or whether you're using it to come up
with an answer which then you aren't
responsible for and you can say you know
the model told me this I mean putting it
bluntly but obviously the major problem
with with with cost benefit analysis in
transport is you have to you have to
make all kinds of assumptions about the
benefit of of you know going half an
hour quicker or of having fewer people
in your in your uh Railway carriage or
over what period of time you're going to
do it we we know that most major
projects have always overrun costs have
always been heavily criticized at at the
time uh the Sydney Opera House is quite
a good example in a completely uh iconic
building but was a total disaster when
when it people first played music in it
Etc and and obviously we have things
closer to home in the UK at the moment
which have this problem so I think where
conviction narrative Theory can can help
you with that process is by first of all
helping you to look at try to dissect
your narrative where are you getting
your conviction from and which bits of
the information you're getting which
narratives are you know giving up are
being considered compelling which
narratives are not being discussed what
points of view for example you know the
workingclass people through whom the
freeway goes and not being and not being
taken into account um uh Etc um so I
think it can assist with thinking around
decisions and with using formal methods
which I'm I'm absolutely not against
using formal methodologies but using
them properly and checking out they work
in the
context cool all right another question
from the live chat so shagor
writes even if on average generating
Alpha returns are not possible is there
work that identifies selected investors
such as Warren Buffett and others that
have consistently identified asset
mispricing wouldn't identifying
investors that are able to consistently
spot mispricing support conviction
narrative Theory I.E sophisticated or
successful investors might understand
how the narrative could
change well so I you know I haven't done
the research on uh uh on uh whether or
not there are consistently success
investors but as I understand the
literature and it's pretty
consistent um the answer is no there
aren't any consistently successful
investors uh and those who are
successful eventually aren't I mean I
happen to have as a quite a close friend
of mine George Soros who is one of the
people who did very well but he also
failed if you talk to him he he he he
failed and uh uh of course once you get
like Warren
Buffett it's complicated there because
if Warren Buffett does something you
know it other people do it and so but
it's of course possible as all the
statisticians on the um on the on the
listening to this would tell there's no
problem having a few outliers
statistically it doesn't tell you that
it's anything to do with those
individual people I mean it might
uh so conviction narrative theory is
is
is would be would explain how people
manage to persuade themselves and each
other that their active form of
investment works and it would also help
to be used to
identify the basis of their claim um but
on the whole I think
um
uh you can understand a great deal of
what goes on in the F in the financial
markets by deploying the concepts of
fantastic object that I mentioned um
integrated State and divided State
because in an integrated State it's very
difficult to do investment very
difficult
indeed for the reason you said in your
questions to me you know you said well
obviously having 20 people in the room
isn't necessarily help but you can
convince yourself it helps and and I can
tell you there are some incredibly
imaginative people out there who work
incredibly hard so one person I
interviewed he had not only got his team
of 20 but he'd assigned them different
roles to to be for and against things to
do this calculation other to play Jokers
when uh they want wanted to make a
particularly strong point and he paid
them according to the way they behaved
and so on they worked really hard to try
and get it right but it didn't it didn't
end up he was convinced but it it didn't
end up over the long term being any
better than any other
way interesting so even from our ACM
post we've seen some inroads into
cognitive economics where people are
drawing from the recent developments
over the last decades in cognitive
science the pragmatic turn extended
embedded enacted and cultured affective
all of these different features that are
increasingly being understood in the
context of human
cognition as well as nonhuman cognition
biological or synthetic or otherwise
so where where does economics go
as it also takes this cognitive turn how
have you seen economics play a role from
what you've worked on over the decades
and then like how would it have been
different if there would have been this
cognitive turn
earlier or how will it be different
going forward as there's more of a
engagement with economics and cognitive
science
so I think so I I think first of all
microeconomics uh microeconomics in in
its sort of best
light uh has small
models that
tell um Illuminating stories about the
relationships between certain I mean
simplest one is supply and demand um and
it it tells useful stor is however the
question
is is that model working in any
particular situation you're in so even
supply and demand you know what if the I
mean the model is still true but it may
not explain the situation you're trying
to deal with and it occurs to me while
he was speaking actually one very
interesting example so there is a there
is a high level academic group that was
uh set up to look radical
uncertainty which has um has on it many
people much more eminent than me on both
sides of the Atlantic and on one
occasion uh a very well-known American
Behavior EC colist presented the work on
gambling that you alluded to and gave
the group sort of you know uh the same
test that he'd given to his Harvard
economics class earlier that week
right he was completely astonished when
this group of people didn't give the
answers that he was expecting and he got
out of his very intelligent Harvard
graduate class and the reason was that
people said things like well if that bet
was available I know the bank wouldn't
pay
out and in other words they thought
round the problem for things
institutional constraints so that they
didn't just think of the problem very
narrowly framed whereas obviously the
The Graduate students were being trained
to think narrowly which can be which can
be useful right um so I I think where
the the fundamental issue with economics
since I studied it back in the late 60s
is that it's become entirely nearly
entirely modelbased there are of course
exceptions but the the sort of high
Prestige of the discipline is in
producing a model and if you read the
papers they're often like this let's
approach it with a simple model we'll
have one person you know and and they're
always simple models there are always
lots and lots of assumptions they um
they they work very nicely but it's
totally unclear how you apply them to
the kind of world that I'm talking about
and
meanwhile what economics doesn't do very
much of is actually go out into the real
world and actually look at what happens
what people do so the study I did of
fund managers you would have thought
someone you know I mean I'm an amateur
right you would have thought someone in
financial economics would have done this
a long time
before uh but they haven't they they
they write lots of paper they do lots of
analysis of very large data sets and
things like that but they don't actually
look and see well how are people how are
people doing it so I think one of my
hopes would be that it would it's it's
not that you don't want models but you
need to understand a lot more about the
human context in which they're being
used and in particular I
think uh you know typical discussions of
Behavioral economics for example is you
know you compare rational and irrational
Behavior where rational means entirely
modelbased right which wouldn't
necessarily be rational in ordinary
terms and irrational means anything else
now if you can't apply probabilities the
whole model doesn't doesn't really start
I think that this restricts thinking
about well how do how does emotion for
example enter into decision making and
and there's there are a lot of studies
in the management literature of what
happened to noia you remember Nokia were
producing mobile phones and they were
producing most of the nogar phones on
the planet and then suddenly there
weren't and this happened pretty quickly
and that some of the arguments about it
concern complex emotional issues in the
company where the people who had done
very well for Nokia over many years were
essentially Engineers who built really
good kit but they didn't understand and
hadn't they were neither listening to
the market so they weren't like the
people trying to sell the things and nor
were they software Engineers so they
hadn't yet understood that actually the
hardware doesn't matter much it's the
software because you know if you compare
many of those old NOK phones to an Apple
I mean the nokas were engineering
Superior things in many ways but the
apple of course one with all the things
it could do so um I I think you can you
know you need to there need to be many
more studies of this kind in my
opinion yeah what you said there about
there being Legacy prestige in
presenting
model-based local
decontextualized variability reduced
analyses reminds me of ant foraging
models where it seems like every single
Paper can present a simple model of a
single
context making many explicit and
implicit assumptions and then the loop
is not always closed by going back out
there so I guess my question is how do
narrative
models help us or what else do we need
to supplement or
complement potentially very
sophisticated cognitive narrative
modeling
because if you point to that phenomena
in the setting of matrix-based Game
Theory modeling and people think that
just by constructing that model that
it's an open and shut case well now
here's a more shiny and feature laad in
type of modeling that seems to cut
closer to the real Crux of the issue
with sense making on the inbound and
action selection on the outbound so how
do we
work so that cognitive modeling or
narrative modeling doesn't also fall
into that trap where people just present
a simplified cognitive
model and then continue the
[Music]
same kind of um epistemic
Gestalt in how it's deployed so what
else is needed beyond the model or what
sits beside the
model well so I don't know whether this
is really a very good answer but but uh
I've never been more than a part-time
academic which is no doubt bad thing in
some way but I I think the really
fascinating so so you know models can
can at least claim to give you a general
truth and the problem about General
truth is it may not apply to any
specific situation right but it people
many people find it
elegant I actually find real interest in
problem
solving and
particularly when you've got I mean I
think interdisciplinary work is
fascinating it's not fascinating when
you all sit around and each person
presents you know how their discipline
does it that tends to get boring after a
while but if you've got a problem to
solve for some someone or or or you know
a problem then you start to really get
to grips with what the different people
can bring to the table you know and I've
been very impressed for example working
with Lenny Smith and Erica Thompson who
are
these weather forecasting mathematician
modelers um the way they manag to frame
and formulate questions is just
fantastic I mean
I think models can help you think very
clearly about things including thinking
where the weaknesses in a particular
system are and I think that that's what
you could add to the narrative theory is
really doing research to try and unpick
the detail of the narratives people are
putting forward and to understand you
know that diagram I put up is a very
complex diagram but actually digging
into in any given case such as you know
the decision to abandon in the UK um
particular Railway project or or or the
decision whether or not to um you know
what what we should be doing about
Heating and insulation over the you know
these kind of big questions you they're
bound to be lots of narratives then
could you actually look at them very
carefully and subject them to to the
kind of rigorous thinking that you get
in this cognitive modeling and so on
that that I think is the way forward but
I think to do that you have to work
actually together on the same problem
then you learn from each
other cool and definitely a theme that
on one hand doesn't seem to be the
formal kernel of active inference yet we
see it arising again and again like for
pragmatism to Blossom there has to be a
real problem in a real situation and a
real approach and it has to be iterated
it's not a spectator sport
to work um son of spectator sport to be
on the field yeah but I think that's a
very cool topic um well where do you go
from here like what Avenues of research
with your um with Carl friston's via
negativ uh
endorsement where do you see this line
of work
heading I I think it's got quite a lot
of I mean there obviously there's room
in economics there's also room in what
was mentioned about
um Futures and foresight science
um and what I hope is people will use
the framework to do empirical work I
mean I I don't think you can really ever
imagine asking the question is
conviction narrative theory true or
false I mean it it seems to me with most
high level theories of that sort what it
it it
usefully is an
orientation onto a problem or a set of
problems which is very different than
standard Theory it doesn't mean standard
Theory should be replaced by conviction
narrative Theory but it means that the
range of questions and research that
people might be doing could be
considerably
broadened I mean that's not a wonderful
answer but that that's basically uh I I
think the other problem is that to do
this stuff properly you need you know
I've had in my
team two or three psychologists a
computer scientist and mathematician and
a um and and a social anthropologist but
I've never had enough resources to have
them all at
once and that's the problem of
interdisciplinary research you actually
need a bigger team and and and then the
team has to work together which is also
complicated so um I I would say that's
another very important implication that
that it's too easy at the moment to work
in a um in a Dugout or in a in a
what you said there about conviction
narrative Theory it can't be simply
validated or invalidated by empirical
evidence it's a lot like active
inference active inference isn't waiting
to be established or disestablished
based upon a measurement from a real
system however you described conviction
narrative Theory as an orienting tool we
could even think about that in terms of
the UDA Loop like observe Orient okay we
Ober OB erve the publication we've
oriented to it we've updated our
cognitive model and now the decision and
the action are where the specifics come
into play because someone could deploy
narrative conviction and then say that
this entity has this conviction and that
may be empirically true or false and so
it's like all of the validation or
invalidation is
in the realization
exactly but the concept is something
that kind of sits before the
realization and so
that when when it is properly understood
and respected for being
theoretical then it can be like this
Fountain of real testable pragmatic
hypotheses real value being layered over
other results and models
um yet not an account or an explanation
in any specific setting by itself but
it's something that lets us jump off of
that orienting platform into all these
settings that we've just discussed
ranging from like the pure Financial
investing which most people are not
going to directly involve in to the the
transport policy and and climate issues
so it it has a
real scope and it's really cool
just to even hear a little bit about how
it's developed over the years and during
a time of uh at UCL and Beyond
development of the cognitive
Sciences I mean there's one other
obvious application which may concern
all of us is to research policy research
applications and how how research
funding is done um because I think it
can be applied you know because
basically as as we all know you if
you're giving out the money if you're
the one giving out the money you've got
to
develop a conviction narrative that
giving money to X is going to do y is
going to achieve whatever you're trying
to achieve right and at the same time
you can see that what x is doing is
trying to develop a conviction narrative
to persuade you right now one of the
things about many funding councils at
the moment is that they typically talk
about doing Innovative work high risk
you know the various phrases high risk
Innovation Etc and then what they
basically do is give the money to people
who look reliable with a good track
record which are probably contradictions
in
uh contradictory activity which isn't to
say you shouldn't give money to the
usual people but it there's clearly a
problem I mean I for example on the book
I put my slide up minding the markets
you'll see that it was very that George
aof as a Nobel prizewinning Economist
was kind enough to endorse it and when I
was talking with
him uh he said that his Nobel paper had
been turned down by three journals I
think it was and when he got to the
dinner for the Nobel laurates there were
three or four others at the table who
had all had the same experience
so of course there are lots of bad ideas
that don't get funded but the issue of
how people develop conviction which is
really how do they manage doubt and
doubt and Poss the possibility your
reputation will you know if you if you
give money to some incompetent group who
waste it all right that your reputation
will suffer and we know if you go to
whiteall if you go to to government
people are terribly worried about
failing and one of the things I hope
conviction narrative uh Theory would do
is to help people to see that if you
want to succeed you've actually got to
fail if you're always succeeding you
can't be trying hard
enough I really like this research
funding or resource allocation setting
there's like these nested conviction
narratives like at the largest scale
like we believe that funding basic
research or fundamental research or
translational research is going to be
beneficial along these ways it's like
we're convinced of that and we're going
to we're we're hodling on that and then
at the program level we have a suspicion
that this or that aspect of this
phenomena is something that the program
manager is going to get behind and that
the resources are all aligned and then
like in the review itself
we might as well directly ask like to
the proposer what are you convinced of
and then not like just what are the
risks or uncertainty or what makes you
avoidant but like what are you convicted
of that makes you charge into that
uncertainty and super excited to carry
out the research and we want to hear
about the fuzziness and uncertainty
because we don't even know simple things
until after the fact so we don't expect
you to have the whole plan but at the
same time it's like we do need to know
that your team and context is convinced
so that you'll continue the
approach as uncertainty
occurs rather than upfront so much
consideration of the uncertainty that
you might never begin and then that sets
up a narrative where even small
experimental perturbations which might
be on the path to transformative
research that those have a negative
veilance rather than like an almost
motivational veilance and and that's
just like that's one example that could
come into play in funding allocation
immediately yeah I think I I think
there's a lot of you know that's a very
practical area where it can be really
thought
about do you have any final comments
no it's been nice talking to you and uh
I do have I I I do find active inference
very interesting and um it kind
of it's at a feeling level it feels
right to
me we may even use conviction narrative
in the act of inference education
setting that's like you could do a 100
phds in thermodynamics and you still
wouldn't have some bar of gold waiting
for you at the end that's like oh now I
understand equation 2.6 so what is it
then that keeps us adding those layers
of paint in our Learning Journey I think
it's an it's an
excellent thought and approach and
sentiment and also if you provide the
slides um there will request in the chat
then I can post them alongside the video
so thank you thank you than you very
much Daniel thank you everyone see you
bye